<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ahitophel's policy defeated a sermon preached on the 9th of September, being the day appointed by His Majesty for a publick thanksgiving for his kingdoms great deliverance from the late treasonable conspiracy against his sacred person and government.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26303</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A439A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19991</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12608473</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12608473</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64295</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26303)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64295)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 339:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ahitophel's policy defeated a sermon preached on the 9th of September, being the day appointed by His Majesty for a publick thanksgiving for his kingdoms great deliverance from the late treasonable conspiracy against his sacred person and government.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W. Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Samuel, 2nd, V, 12 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64295:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Ahitophel's Policy Defeated.</hi> A SERMON Preached on the <hi>9th</hi> of <hi>September,</hi> Being the Day appointed by His MAJESTY for a <hi>Publick Thankſgiving</hi> For HIS and the KINGDOMS GREAT DELIVERANCE From the late Treaſonable CONSPIRACY Againſt His Sacred Perſon and Government.</p>
            <q>
               <p>For it was not an Enemy that reproached me, then I could have born it: neither was it be that hated me that did magnifie himſelf againſt me; then I would have hid my ſelf from him. But it was thou, one whom I eſteemed as my ſelf, my guide, and my acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, we took ſweet counſel together.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſalm. LV. 12, 13, 14.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Regum exitus ſi reputaverimus, plures à ſuis quàm ab hoſtibus interemptos reperiemus.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Quint. Curt. L. IX.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>—Non creditur niſi perpetratum facinus.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Liv. L. XL.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>W. Kettilby</hi> at the Biſhops Head in S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1683.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:64295:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:64295:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 Sam. XV. 12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And Abſalom ſent for Ahitophel the Gilonite, Davids Counſellour, from his City, even from Giloh, while he offered Sacrifices: and the Conſpiracy was ſtrong; for the people increaſed continually with Abſalom.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WE read in the XIII. Chapter of this Book, that <hi>Abſalom</hi> (having kill'd his Brother <hi>Ammon</hi> for defiling his Siſter <hi>Tamar</hi>) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently fled unto <hi>Geſhur</hi> in <hi>Syria,</hi> where he continued ſome time with King <hi>Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mai,</hi> his Grandfather by the Mother's ſide. <hi>Ammon</hi> was elder Brother, and therefore (conſidering <hi>Abſalom</hi>'s aſpiring Genius) 'tis probable that he committed this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricide, rather out of an Ambition he had to be the more nearly related to the Crown, than any Vertuous Deteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Brothers ſin. Such as God was ſometimes pleas'd to put into the hearts of the Jewiſh Zealots. However he takes this occaſion to remove him out of the way, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he juſtly feared that his Father <hi>David</hi> would not let ſo foul a Fact go unpuniſh'd, he flyes from his preſence, and returns not again to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> till about three years after.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Joab</hi> (perceiving the King's Affections towards his Son) by the Parable which he put into the mouth of the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of <hi>Tekoah,</hi> prevail'd with the King to iſſue out Order for bringing him back again to the Imperial City. So <hi>Joab a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64295:3"/>and went to Geſhur, and brought Abſalom to Jeruſalem. Ch.</hi> XIV. v. 23. Where after he had reſided about two years, he is permitted to ſee the King's face, and is graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly receiv'd into favour. Good King <hi>David</hi> could not caſt off the bowels and tenderneſs of a Father, tho' he, unnatural Child! abandon's all the Duty of a Son: for inſtead of repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for what he had done, he ſeconds his former ſin with another of a more hainous nature, to Murther he adds Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion. And he who before had illegally kill'd his Brother, does now, both againſt all the Laws of God and man, wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly Conſpire againſt his own Father.</p>
            <p>For this purpoſe he <hi>prepares Chariots, and Horſes, and fifty men,</hi> to guard his body from the aſſaults of his Enemies, that is, the Kings Friends. And (becauſe he well knew that his Deſign would not take Effect, unleſs the Multitude were drawn into the Deſign) by fair ſpeeches, and flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring inſinuations, he <hi>Steals away the Peoples hearts from his Father David.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And leſt his ſecret Machinations ſhould be diſcover'd, he reſolves to quit <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> Accordingly he begs and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains leave to depart. And to cover his black Deſigns with a fair Appearance, he alledges Religion as the Cauſe of his removal. <hi>I pray thee</hi> (ſays he unto the King) <hi>let me go and pay my Vow, which I have vowed unto the Lord in Hebron.</hi> The pious King was glad to find his Son ſo well diſpos'd, hopeing that now he would ſeriouſly repent of his former wickedneſs. He therefore eaſily granted his requeſt, and <hi>ſaid unto him, go in peace. So he aroſe and went to Hebron.</hi> When he was come thither, he ſends for <hi>Ahitophel,</hi> that cunning Politician. And now Wit and Strength, Judgment and Courage being united, no wonder that the People dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly flock'd to <hi>Abſalom,</hi> and that great numbers continually liſted themſelves into the Conſpiracy. <hi>And Abſalom ſent for Ahitophel the Gilonite, Davids Counſellour, from his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64295:3"/>City, even from Giloh, while he offered ſacrifices: and the Conſpiracy was ſtrong, for the People encreaſed continually with Abſalom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall conſider the words with relation unto the Context, and therefore ſhall not ſtrictly bind my ſelf within the compaſs of this Verſe, but repreſent this Conſpiracy as it is more fully deſcribed in this, and the following Chapters, where we have an Account, (I.) Of the Heads, and Chief Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moters of it, (II.) Of the Perſon againſt whom it was deſign'd, (III.) The Pretences by which it was carry'd on, (IV.) The Progreſs which was made in it, And (V.) how at laſt it was happily Diſcover'd and Defeated.</p>
            <p n="1">(I.) The Chief Heads and Promoters of it were <hi>Abſalom</hi> and <hi>Ahitophel,</hi> two whoſe Qualifications render'd them fit both to project and execute this horrid Conſpiracy. For who amongſt all the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> more likely to go further in a Rebellion, than <hi>Abſalom;</hi> whoſe Birth and Beauty, plauſible Carriage, and undauntd Courage ſeem'd to ſpeak him a King at the firſt ſight, and Challenge the higheſt place of Honour, as a Reward naturally due unto his great Accompliſhments?</p>
            <p n="1">1. By Birth we find that he was the King's Son, tho' not the <hi>Immediate Succeſſour:</hi> For <hi>David</hi> had another Son elder than he was, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> III. 3. But no matter whether the Title be lawful or no. Ambition ſtays not to Examine ſuch ſmall Punctilio's. In his own Thoughts he's the moſt deſerving, and he's already Crown'd in the Peoples Favour. Why ſhould he ſtand upon the niceties of Law, when his own Merits, and the Voice of the Multitude have already de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd him King? And what <hi>Conſecration</hi> can be more Sacred than this, wherein Intrinſick Worth, and External Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony do both concur? Shall the Plea of <hi>Hereditary Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion</hi> be admitted againſt a Claim Seal'd in Heaven, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim'd on Earth by <hi>God's Repreſentatives, the People?</hi> I am
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64295:4"/>the King's Son (as we may ſuppoſe <hi>Abſalom</hi> arguing the caſe with himſelf) and tho' there be another elder than I am, yet, being neither fit to Govern, nor Beloved of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the Priviledge which he has by Birth is cancell'd; and therefore the Right of Succeſſion devolves upon me, who am the next in order. I have the Royal Blood in my Veins as well as he, and none of thoſe Impediments which diſanuls his <hi>Birthright,</hi> and make him altogether uncapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be <hi>King of Iſrael.</hi> Thus we may ſuppoſe <hi>Abſalom's</hi> ambitious Thoughts roving beyond all the Sacred Bounds of God's Laws, to find out new Arguments whereby he might prove, that he, and not his Elder Brother, was by eſpecial Providence deſign'd to Succeed in the <hi>Throne of his Father David.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. And as by Birth he was the King's Son, ſo he had other Advantages which did not a little encourage him in his Treaſonable Attempt. His fair and comely Feature ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd him amiable in the Eyes of Men, and did ſilently plead his Cauſe with thoſe who <hi>Judge according to appearance, and not righteous Judgment.</hi> Amongſt all the Children of, <hi>Iſrael</hi> he was reputed the Faireſt, and therefore by the Vulgar, who judge more by Senſe than Reaſon, would be accounted the moſt Deſerving. And indeed a Beautiful and Graceful Viſage is apt to beget a ſecret love and eſteem in Wiſer men. Virtuous Habits ſhine more Illuſtriouſly through a Beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Countenance, and receive ſome Additional Grace from a well-proportion'd Body. And on the other ſide, nothing is more dangerous than Painted ſin: For the deformities of Vice, cover'd over with a lovely Meen, will paſs for the fair Embelliſhments of Virtue; ſo that the unwary Admirer of the one, is ſoon tainted with the other; whilſt his Fancy is pleas'd, his Judgment is defil'd, and he ſwallows the moſt poyſonous Drugs under the Name and Colour of Golden Pills. He therefore who abuſes theſe Gifts of Nature,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64295:4"/>and uſes them not as Recommendations of Virtue, but Entice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments unto Sin, does waſte his Talent, and has reaſon to fear, that hereafter he ſhall find the Reward of a <hi>wicked</hi> and <hi>faithleſs Servant.</hi> Theſe graceleſs Servants, who inſtead of improving, do miſemploy their Endowments, are highly Injurious unto the Lord of Heaven and Earth, and at the laſt day will be miſerably confounded, when he ſhall <hi>require his own with uſury.</hi> If none be to be ſo much prais'd as <hi>Abſalom</hi> for his Beauty, and none ſo much to be condemned for his uncomely Qualities: If from the <hi>crown of the head to the ſole of the foot, there be no blemiſh in him;</hi> and yet all the Actions of his life be very ugly, and fouly miſhapen: the Symmetry of his body will ſerve only to aggravate the Irregularities of his mind. If the <hi>Phariſee's</hi> Hands be waſh'd, when his Heart is full of all manner of Corruption, he's ſtill a <hi>Phariſee,</hi> and ſhall receive the Woe denounc'd againſt ſuch hypocritical Sinners: for tho' he may deceive ſhort-ſighted Men, he cannot impoſe upon the All-ſeeing God. He may Cheat his Neighbour, who looks on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on the out-ſide; but not him, who diſcerns all the ſecrets of our hearts.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Another advantage in <hi>Abſalom's</hi> perſon, was his Plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Carriage and Popular Behaviour: <hi>When any man came nigh him to do him obeiſance, he put forth his hand, and took him, and kiſſed him,</hi> Ch. XV. v. 5.</p>
            <p>A courteous and friendly Deportment towards Inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours (if it proceed from a natural temper) is a ſign of an ingenuous diſpoſition. But if it be an Habit fix'd upon the Principles of Morality and true Religion, is an admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Vertue, and moſt attractive of common approbation. He who is ſenſible that Humanity and Gentleneſs is a common Debt, will not confine his Civility, to them who are above, but will ſuffer it to deſcend on thoſe below him. He will treat all Perſons with temperate and calm Language;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64295:5"/>neither flattering his Betters, nor deſpiſing thoſe who move in a leſſer Sphere. He knows how to put a Juſt Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue upon himſelf, without the Unjuſt Contempt of others, and does not think a Diſdainful and Proud Behaviour to be a neceſſary Qualification of an <hi>Accompliſh'd Gentleman.</hi> He as much avoids the Moroſeneſs of the ſullen Stoick, as the Vanity of the light <hi>Epicurean.</hi> Having firſt ſought himſelf in his own Conſcience, and endeavour'd to approve himſelf unto God; as he does not ſeek, ſo he doth altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſdain other men's eſteem, if he can <hi>Pleaſe them for their good to edification;</hi> or (which by the way is the true meaning of Edification) can thereby build them up in their Chriſtian Faith, in the Communion of the <hi>one Holy Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick-Church.</hi> Had <hi>Abſalom</hi>'s obligeing Carriage been foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon this Principle, and directed onely to this End, no wiſe Man would have blam'd his Conduct. But when his Popularity ſprang from a rotten and corrupt heart, and was deſign'd to inveigle men into a treacherous Conſpiracy: When he complemented the People only in order to his own Greatneſs, and his Father's Ruine. All his fair Words, and taking Geſtures, were but ſo many Artificial Tricks of <hi>Leger-de-main,</hi> whereby he ſtole away the Hearts of the People from his Father, and of Loyal Subjects transform'd them into Revolting Rebels. As the Lion is moſt Couchant, when his Aims are moſt bloody; ſo he put on the Guiſe of the greateſt Meekneſs and Humility; that, with greater advantage, he might ſeiſe upon his prey. <hi>He fell down and humbled himſelf, that the Congregation of the poor might fall into the hands of his Captains,</hi> Pſal. X. 11.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In the next place we may obſerve, That <hi>Abſalom</hi>'s ſtout Courage, and manly Reſolutions, prompted him to Engage, and promiſe unto himſelf Succeſs, in ſuch a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Undertaking. His High Spirit could not well brook any Equal, much leſs a Superiour, tho' it was his own
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64295:5"/>Father; who by a triple Right, Natural, Civil, and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, might have commanded his Obedience. This three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Cord (one would think) might have bound his extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant Paſſions to their good behaviour. But, alas! what Obligations are ſtrong enough to reſtrain the unruly Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of an hard-mouth'd Courage? What ſignifies Reaſon, Law, and Duty on the one ſide, or the proſpect of Danger on the other, to a Valiant Heart enflamed with the Fire of Ambition? Such an one ſees no Obſtacles either of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence or Difficulty in the way; therefore he preſſes on with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either wit or fear, and doubts not but that he ſhall ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther find, or make an eaſie paſſage unto his deſir'd King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Had <hi>Abſalom</hi> ſat down, and calmly conſider'd with himſelf what an horrid Crime it was to Depoſe his Lawful Soveraign, and deareſt Parent; how hard a matter the Subverſion of a well ſettl'd Kingdom was likely to prove; how ſtrongly Princes are guarded by the <hi>King of Kings,</hi> and <hi>Lord of Lords;</hi> and how frequently the Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence doth detect and confound the Deſigns of Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Sons and Rebellious Subjects: Had he ſeriouſly weigh'd theſe things, he would have found that his fancy'd Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and Greatneſs in one Scale, was not able to counter-ballance the Sin and Danger of this Conſpiracy in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But what Reaſon and Conſideration can be expected from Brutal Courage, and Armed Madneſs? From Natural Strength heated with the Feaveriſh Imaginations of <hi>Crowns</hi> and <hi>Scepters?</hi> This High and Daring Diſpoſition <hi>Abſalom</hi>'s Politick-Drivers ſaw, and abuſed. His heady Reſolution and inconſiderate Boldneſs made him (they knew very well) the fitter Inſtrument to actuate their Malice. They give Advice, and he is to undertake the Combats. They Contrive, and he is to Act within thoſe Lines which they have Chalked-out. As his Blood ſerv'd to Countenance, ſo his Great Spirit to Animate their Wicked Intentions. Out
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64295:6"/>of his Diſcontented Paſſion, his Counſellors wrought their own Ends; and (as it often happens unto Young and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Diſpoſitions) entangled him in their Old and moſt Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honourable Deſigns. But ſuch men ſhall ſurely anſwer not only for themſelves, but alſo thoſe whom they have Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced. If <hi>Abſalom,</hi> by the Management of a Faithful Counſellour, might in his Station have become an Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Country, and by <hi>Ahitophel</hi>'s wicked Inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions is made the worſt of Subjects, ſuch wretched Tutors ſhall be reſponſible for the pernicious Principles of their perverted Pupils.</p>
            <p>And if we Conſider <hi>Ahitophel's</hi> Character, it will appear that none of all <hi>David</hi>'s Counſellors was ſo fit and likely to debauch the Mind of this Young Diſciple, and ſo become the Great Engineer of this Conſpiracy, as this <hi>Arch-Politician.</hi> For, 1. he had been <hi>David</hi>'s <hi>Counſellour,</hi> or the Preſident, (it's poſſible) of that Honourable Board, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> XXVII. 33. Upon this Account, he (being a Man of Penetrating Wit) muſt needs have been well acquainted with the Methods of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>'s Counſels, the Poſture of his Affairs, his Particular In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations, and all the Defects as well as Accompliſhments of his Perſon. So that he could inform <hi>Abſalom</hi> how to Provide againſt his Strength, as well as Aſſault him in the Weakeſt Place. 'Tis no ſmall advantage unto thoſe who Meditate a Rebellion, to underſtand the Temper of their Prince, the Qualifications of his Prime Miniſters, and the State of his Government: for by this means their Impious Projects are more likely to take Effect. Thus they may lay their Plots ſo, as to be leaſt Suſpected by the King; may, perhaps, prevail with ſome of his Familiar Friends to betray him; but moſt Certainly take all Occaſions, with greater Security, to diſturb the Government. And we may be ſure that <hi>Ahitophel</hi> (who 'twas well known, omitted no Opportunities which made for his Purpoſe) gave no ſmall
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64295:6"/>Encouragement to the Cauſe, by the Knowledge which he had of State-matters, and his dextrous Art in applying all his Underſtanding to the Deſign which he was Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd to Manage. Eſpecially, 2. At this Time, being a a Diſcontented Courtier, doubtleſs he ſtrain'd his Wit, to invent how he might Revenge himſelf upon <hi>Good King Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid.</hi> Therefore finding <hi>Abſalom</hi> in the Heat of Youth, greedy of Soveraignty, and Extreamly Diſcontented with his Foul Diſgrace at Court, and long Baniſhment; He pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently Joynes Iſſue with him, aggravates the Father's Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſs, repreſents the Sons Innocence, and with all Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetick Expreſſions, which Malice could ſuggeſt, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to raiſe <hi>Abſalom</hi> unto the higheſt Pitch of Indignation: That ſo the Breach betwixt him and his Father might be beyond the Poſſibility of a Reconciliation. Time might have Moderated <hi>Abſalom</hi>'s high Paſſions, and worn out <hi>David</hi>'s Diſpleaſure conceiv'd againſt him. But <hi>Ahitophel</hi>'s Diabolical Cunning took Care to Prevent all Hopes of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement: Accordingly he adds Fuel to the Fire, and inſtead of quenching, blows the Coals of the Conſpiracy, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the Chief Manager, as, Queſtionleſs, he was the firſt Deſigner of it. For tho' there is no Mention of <hi>Ahitophel</hi>'s Conſulting with <hi>Abſalom</hi> before he ſent for him to <hi>Hebron;</hi> yet this doth not exclude Former Debates about the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. And indeed it is not probable that <hi>Abſalom,</hi> had he not been before aſſur'd of his Utmoſt Aſſiſtance, wou'd have made him his Intimate Companion at <hi>Hebron,</hi> and there have imparted to him his moſt Secret Counſels. He knew, before this Meſſage, that he was ſtrongly link'd to his Faction, as well as, that he was a Man of Deep Reach, and great Judgment in State Affairs. 3. Which is another thing that fitted him to be a Principal in this Rebellion. <hi>The Counſel of Ahitophel</hi> (ſayes the Text) <hi>was as if a Man had enquired at the Oracle,</hi> (or the word) <hi>of God.</hi> So it had
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64295:7"/>been with <hi>David,</hi> and ſo now it was with <hi>Abſalom,</hi> Chap. XVI. 23. He was ſo eſteem'd for his Wiſdom, that his Counſels were receiv'd, as if they had all been Divine Truths and Reveal'd from Heaven. His Advice was generally ſeconded with ſutable Succeſs, therefore it was ſo highly Reverenc'd; and not becauſe in it ſelf it always Deſerved to be ſo much applauded. For this Counſel which here he gave <hi>Abſalom,</hi> was ſo far from being Divine, that it was moſt Damnably wicked; tho', in the Policy of it, moſt Exquiſitely Pernicious. So that the Wiſdome for which he was ſo highly admired, was not really that which <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcends from above, Pure</hi> and <hi>Peaceable:</hi> but that <hi>Earthly Wiſdom</hi> which is <hi>Senſual</hi> and <hi>Deviliſh.</hi> He was acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with all the Turns and Intrigues, the Windeings and Doublings, the Paſſions and Principles of Crooked Nature. He was very well Skill'd in all the Frauds, Impoſtures and Vices of Mankind; Had all the Wiſdome of the Serpent, but nothing of the Dove-like Innocence. He acted by ſuch Maxims as theſe: <hi>Virtue is not much to be regarded, but only it's appearance, becauſe the Name and Opinion of Virtue may be an Help, but Virtue is an Impediment.</hi> That a <hi>True Politician ought to make all Obnoxious, and draw them on his ſide, by engaging them in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>npardonable Villanies.</hi> That <hi>an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act Stateſman ſhou'd be Concern'd only for himſelf, and Care not (if he be Safe in the Ship) whether others ſink or ſwim.</hi> In a word, he was the moſt accompliſh'd <hi>Machiavilian</hi> of his Time. He who ſeem'd to be an Oracle of God, was, in truth, rather inſpired by that Infernal Spirit who Actuated the Oracle at <hi>Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phos:</hi> And tho' he appear'd as an Angel of Light, yet really was one of the ſubtle Agents of the Prince of Darkneſs.</p>
            <p>And now, was not he, who had been <hi>David</hi>'s Chief Counſellour; at preſent a Diſcontented Courtier; and was ſo well Vers'd in all the Arts of a Crafty Politician; was not he moſt likely to eſpouſe, and moſt able to manage <hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom</hi>'s Faction againſt the Holy <hi>David?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:64295:7"/> (II.) Who was the Perſon againſt whom this Horrid Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion was Intended; who all this while lay ſecure, ſooner Expecting the Invaſion of a Foreign Enemy, than a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy headed by his Deareſt Son. His indulgent Affection would not ſuffer him to entertain ſuch a Thought of the Young Man, whom he ſo Entirely loved. <q>What, is <hi>Abſalom</hi> amongſt the Conſpirators? 'tis not poſſible that he ſhould be ſo Monſtrouſly Ingrateful. Is he not my Subject, my Friend, and my Child? And can he ſo ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly forget all theſe Relations, as to Deſign againſt my Life, who am his King, his Benefactor, and his Aged Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? Will he Ruine me, who am Contriving his Well-being? What can he Propoſe to himſelf by my Death, but Eternal Shame and Ignomie? What can he think will be the Conſequence of ſuch an Accurſed Cruelty, but his own Everlaſting Deſtruction? Why then ſhould I Entertain ſuch Hard Thoughts of him, poor Young-Man! Can he either be ſo Fooliſh or ſo Profligately Wicked, as to Endeavour at once both to Undo me and himſelf?</q> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this Manner (it's probable) that the <hi>Good King</hi> reaſon'd with himſelf till Treaſon loudly Knock'd at his Gates; and he was Certainly inform'd by a Special Meſſenger, that <hi>the Hearts of the Men of Iſrael were after Abſalom.</hi> Now he is fully Convinc'd of the Truth of that, which his Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ingenuity would not eaſily ſuffer him to Believe. But how (may we ſuppoſe) did this ſtrange News pierce his afflicted Soul? The Curſes of <hi>Shimei,</hi> and the Reproaches of <hi>Goliah,</hi> were but eaſy tryals of his Patience, when Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd with this Son of his own Bowels, who had Rebelled againſt him.</p>
            <p>But beſides this Eſpecial Relation, which did require <hi>Abſalom</hi>'s Obedience, <hi>David</hi> was <hi>King of all Iſrael;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the People were bound to give unto him the things which belong unto <hi>Caeſar: Cuſtom, Tribute, Reverence,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64295:8"/>Loyalty,</hi> and <hi>Dutiful Allegiance.</hi> Had he been as bad as <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dekiah,</hi> yet was he <hi>the Breath of their Noſtrils,</hi> and ought to have been Treated as the <hi>Anointed of the Lord, Lam.</hi> IV. 20. Had he been as Wicked as <hi>Nero,</hi> yet he was <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent;</hi> and his Subjects were oblig'd to Obey not only him, <hi>as Supream,</hi> but alſo <hi>his Miniſters as ſent by him,</hi> and this, under no leſs a Penalty than <hi>Damnation.</hi> Had he been the Greateſt Oppreſſour, and moſt Cruel Tyrant, yet who had any Right to ſay unto him, <hi>what doeſt thou? Eccleſ.</hi> VIII. 4. For <hi>againſt a King there is no Riſeing. And who can Stretch out his hand againſt the Lord's Anointed, and be guiltleſs?</hi> Prov. XXX. 31. 1 Sam. XXXVI 9. <hi>Is it fit</hi> (ſaith <hi>Elihu</hi>) <hi>to ſay to a King, thou art wicked, and to Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ye are ungodly? Is it comely, nay is it not highly</hi> Impious, to <hi>Reproach the Footſteps of God's Anointed? Job</hi> XXXIV. 16. <hi>Pſal.</hi> LXXXIX. 51. And as we muſt not Blaſpheme the Sacred Perſons of Kings with our Words, or Aſſault them with our Actions: So neither muſt we Murmur againſt them, or Curſe them, no not in our Thoughts. Thoſe who do ſo, Rebel not only againſt them, but againſt the King of Kings, who hath reſerv'd unto himſelf the Prerogative of Judging, Rebuking, and Puniſhing his Repreſentatives.</p>
            <p>Thus had <hi>David</hi> been one of the wicked Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> yet every Soul was Bound to Reverence his Royal Perſon, and inſtead of Oppoſing him by Force of Arms, was oblig'd to make it part of his Daily Prayer unto God, that he wou'd <hi>grant the King a long Life, even for ever and ever. Neh.</hi> II. 3.</p>
            <p>But if we Conſider him as a moſt <hi>Gracious</hi> and <hi>Merciful, Wiſe</hi> and <hi>Prudent, Juſt</hi> and <hi>Righteous King;</hi> this does hugely aggravate the Guilt of thoſe <hi>Rebellious Iſraelites.</hi> He reſembled God not only in Power, but alſo in Mercy, Wiſdom, and Juſtice, with which his Government was ſo admirably Temper'd; that his Subjects had no cauſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64295:8"/>of thoſe Miſchiefs, which uſually accompany that Princes Reign, which is manag'd with Barbarous Cruelty, unworthy Cunning, and Licentious Toleration. What therefore ſhould move them to Rebel againſt him, who in Virtue as well as Dignity of Place was the <hi>Light of Iſrael, and Worth ten Thouſand of them?</hi> O Fooliſh People, and Unwiſe! do you thus Requite your great Deliverer and Benefactor? Shall <hi>David,</hi> who hath deſtroyed the Mighty Man, and preſerved you from the hand of the <hi>Philiſtins;</hi> ſhall he who hath ſaved you, as well as himſelf from the <hi>Jaws of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and the <hi>Paw of the Bear;</hi> ſhall he, whom God hath mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly protected for your Good; ſhall he be depoſed by you, who Live, Thrive, and Proſper under the kind In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of his Benigne Favour? Do you firſt judge him unfit to Govern, and then Reſolve to rend his Kingdom from him? But where hath God made you Judges f your Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Abilities, and by what Prophet hath he Pulickly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd that his Kingdom ſhall not Continue? To what Man of God hath he given Commiſſion to appoint another During his Reign, as he did to <hi>Samuel,</hi> to anoint <hi>David,</hi> whilſt <hi>Saul</hi> poſſeſt the Kingdom of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> If the Houſe of <hi>Saul</hi> (by God's Expreſs Order) be rejected for his Rebellion againſt God, ſhall therefore <hi>Good King David,</hi> without po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive command from Heaven, be dethron'd by the People? God does not now Transfer Kingdoms from one to another by Immediate Revelation; and when he did ſo, he never gave any Power to the People either to Create, or Depoſe Kings. When he had Choſen <hi>Moſes</hi> to be King in <hi>Jeſharun,</hi> he abhors and is highly offended at thoſe <hi>Factious Levites,</hi> and <hi>famous Members of Parliament, men of Renown,</hi> who ſhall murmur and <hi>Remonſtrate</hi> againſt his proceedings. But not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the ſevere Judgment which God Inflicted upon <hi>Corah,</hi> and his Rebellious Aſſociates; <hi>Abſalom</hi> and <hi>Ahitophel,</hi> with their Rebellious Aſſociates, are Confederates
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64295:9"/>together with one Conſent againſt their Lawful and moſt Gracious Soveraign.</p>
            <p n="3">(III.) And that they may put a Good Face upon their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious Practices; <q>they declar'd that they very Unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enter'd upon theſe Violent Courſes; could they, any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, have redreſs'd theſe Grievances under which the whole Nation lay moſt ſadly Oppreſt. Alas! they could eaſily bear the Affronts and Indignities which <hi>David</hi> (by the Advice of his Evil Counſellours) had put upon them. But when they conſider'd the Oppreſſions with which the Poor People were harraſſed; When their <hi>Ancient Liberties,</hi> and <hi>Juſt Rights,</hi> and (that which ought to be moſt dear unto every <hi>true Iſraelite</hi>) their <hi>Holy Religion (as Reform'd by Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom and Ahitophel at Hebron)</hi> lay at Stake, and were in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to be utterly loſt: When <hi>Iſrael's</hi> Condition was thus Miſerable, they could not but endeavour to relieve their Beloved Countrymen, and doubted not but that all who had any love to their Country, or their Religion, would joyn with them in this <hi>Righteous and Holy Cauſe.</hi> They were very ſenſible that the Followers of <hi>David</hi> would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach them as <hi>Rebels</hi> and <hi>Traytors;</hi> and appropriate unto themſelves the Title of the <hi>Loyal Party:</hi> But this did not move them, who (for the good of their Brethren) were ready not only to be <hi>evil Spoken of;</hi> but to Sacrifice their very <hi>Lives,</hi> and all their <hi>deareſt Concerns</hi> in this World.</q> And now what honeſt, plain and ſimple <hi>Iſraelite</hi> (hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe fair Pretences) wou'd not become a <hi>Proſelyte,</hi> weep over the Miſeries of his Nation, look upon theſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as his only Patriots, and intirely give up himſelf unto their Conduct? Theſe ſweet Words, and gloſing Harangues (eſpecially coming from <hi>Men famous in the Aſſembly</hi>) were enough to Charm the Common and Vulgar, tho' Innocent and Well-meaning People. An Upright Man, in whom was no Guile, would not have ſuſpected any in this Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64295:9"/>When in Truth, it was nothing but an <hi>Artificial Perſwaſive</hi> to draw all Sorts of men into a moſt Horrid and Unnatural Rebellion. A Cabal of <hi>Republicans, Atheiſts,</hi> and <hi>Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks</hi> met together at <hi>Hebron,</hi> and agreed (under the ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Pretences of <hi>Property and Publick Good, Liberties and the Laws, Religion and Reformation</hi>) to invite into the <hi>Faction, the Honeſt</hi> and <hi>Induſtrions;</hi> the <hi>Ingenuous</hi> and <hi>Free-born;</hi> the <hi>Pious</hi> and <hi>Devout.</hi> They were already Aſſured of thoſe who were like unto themſelves in Temper and Principles; and that they might catch others, who in a Lawful Senſe were Friends to <hi>Property, Liberty,</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> they Baited the Hook with theſe Glittering Pretences. <hi>See,</hi> ſays <hi>Abſalom</hi> (after he had Examin'd each Man's Caſe) <hi>thy Matters are good, and right; But there is no man deputed of the King to hear thee;</hi> Or, (as it is in the Margine) <hi>none will hear thee from the King</hi> downward, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> XV. 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> now began to grow in Age, and therefore <hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom</hi> took this Occaſion to render him Odious and Deſpica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble unto the People. When the King Grows Old, the Gid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Multitude are eaſily Perſwaded to deſire a Change; not Conſidering that <hi>David,</hi> by the Wiſdom and Experience of Old-Age, was now better Qualify'd to Rule his Kingdom in Peace, which by the Strength and Valour of his Youth he had before Defended in War. But ſuppoſe that <hi>David,</hi> through the Infirmities of Age, was uncapable to Govern ſo well as in his more Sprightly Youth; doth it become <hi>Abſalom</hi> to expoſe the Nakedneſs of his Father, or <hi>Ahitophel</hi> to Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the Imperfections of his Aged Maſter? Is it the part of an Obedient Son or Faithful Servant, in his Declining Age to Incenſe the People againſt him, and ſo endeavour with <hi>Sorrow to bring down his Gray Hairs unto the Grave?</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps while they were at Court, they had obſerv'd ſome Miſcarriages of <hi>David</hi>'s Officers. What if there were ſome Male-adminiſtrations lyable to juſt Exception? there never
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64295:10"/>was any Government without its Faults; and 'tis not like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that <hi>David</hi>'s Kingdom, tho' an Eminent Type of Chriſt's, was without its Spots and Wrinckles. But muſt the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple therefore he alarm'd with ſad Outcries againſt the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, as if none cou'd have Juſtice, and no man could call any thing, which he poſſeſt, his own? This uſe indeed <hi>Abſalom</hi> makes of the Court-Corruptions, not that he was Concern'd for the Peoples Happineſs, but his own Power and Greatneſs. As it follows, <hi>Oh!, that I were made Judge in the Land, that every man that hath Suite or Cauſe might come unto me: and I will do him Juſtice.</hi> Thus under the Guiſe of Property, and Publick Good, <hi>Abſalom</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to get the Government into his own hands; but ſome of his Adviſers ('tis not unprobable) under this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, intended to turn the <hi>Monarchy</hi> into a <hi>Common-Wealth.</hi> And this Argument, 'twas thought, would Prevail with thoſe to come over to the Party, who were Honeſt and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious; who by lawful means had gotten an Eſtate, and were ('twas to be ſuppos'd) willing to preſerve it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In like manner to gain the Ingenuous, and thoſe who were well Deſcended, We may be aſſured that <hi>Abſalom's</hi> Counſellours caus'd it to be bruited abroad, that King <hi>David</hi> was about to bring in <hi>Arbitrary Government,</hi> and to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all their <hi>Laws, Rights, Priviledges</hi> and <hi>Immunities,</hi> which <hi>they</hi> and <hi>their Fore-fathers</hi> had hitherto enjoy'd. And this, to be ſure, would Create no ſmall Prejudices unto his Royal Perſon, and Authority. What! ſhall we who are a Free born People be Entangled with the Yoke of Bondage? Shall we who are <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed, <hi>and never were in Bondage to any man,</hi> tamely ſuffer our ſelves to be made Vaſſals and Slaves, when we have <hi>Law on our ſides,</hi> and <hi>Power in our Hands,</hi> to Vindicate our own Liberties? If <hi>David</hi> ceaſe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have himſelf as our juſt and merciful King, we do no longer own him the Duty of Subjects. Therefore, <hi>To your Tents, O
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64295:10"/>Iſrael;</hi> let us dye like Men, rather than live like Beaſts of Burthen. We are not now in <hi>Egypt,</hi> but in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and if <hi>David</hi> will be a <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> ſhall we be <hi>Egyptian</hi> Bond-ſlaves? With ſuch like ſtrains as theſe, the Popular Orators drew in to their Faction thoſe <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> who were Well-Born, and had been Ingenuouſly Educated. And tho' in the Hiſtory of this Rebellion, we find no Complaint that their Liberties were Invaded; yet 'tis very likely they made uſe of this Topick, not only becauſe 'tis the uſual, and plauſible Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Place of the Seditious, but alſo becauſe <hi>Solomon's</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment (which was more Eaſy and Peaceable than <hi>David</hi>'s) was, we find, accounted Grievous, and very Hard to be Born. <hi>Thy Father</hi> (ſays <hi>Jeroboam</hi> in the name of all <hi>Iſrael</hi>) <hi>made our Yoke Grievous,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> XII. 4. We may therefore, not without Reaſon, preſume that <hi>Abſalom</hi>'s Agitators did not omit this Occaſion, tho' the Liberty for which they Contended, and really aimed at, might be nothing elſe but an Exemption from all the Laws both of God and Man: ſo that they might (without fear of Puniſhment) have been <hi>Scepticks</hi> in their Opinions, and Libertines in their Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But the greateſt Impoſture was the Pretence of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, ſet on Foot (as we may ſuppoſe) by <hi>Abſalom's Fanatick-Confeſſours,</hi> that ſo their Rebellion might be reputed the Cauſe of Religion, and be ſtrengthen'd with the aſſiſtance of all thoſe, who deſir'd to be accounted the Truly Pious and Devout. For this Purpoſe <hi>Abſalom</hi> muſt feign at leaſt, that he had Vowed, if he ſhould return ſafe to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to praiſe God at <hi>Hebron</hi> for his goodneſs towards him. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly he Sollicites his Father to Conſent unto his Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. The <hi>truly Religious David,</hi> glad to hear that his Son was ſo well diſpos'd, readily grants his Petition, little ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>Hebron,</hi> where Sacrifices, eſpecially Peace-Offerings, uſed to be performed, ſhould be a place deſign'd for a Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64295:11"/>Conſpiracy. But ſo it was; <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was not now a Place Convenient for <hi>Abſalom</hi>'s purpoſe; the Treaſon could not have been long Conceal'd in that City, where <hi>David</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſided. Beſides his Preſence wou'd have daunted the Courage of ſome, and have won the Love of others. Therefore this <hi>Conventicle</hi> at <hi>Hebron</hi> is reſolved upon, as the beſt Means to Unite them all in this moſt Helliſh Conſpiracy. Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs is never ſo bewitching, as when it appears in the Beautiful Robes of Religion. Who would have ſuſpected any harm from this <hi>Holy Aſſembly of the Brother-hood?</hi> Alas! <q>
                  <hi>Abſalom,</hi> Good Man! intends to becom a New Man, reſolves to Repent of all his former ſins, and for this end is come to <hi>Hebron</hi> to Perform this Vow, in a <hi>more pure</hi> way of Worſhip, than he can do at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> And as for the Feaſts and Publick Entertainments which he makes; they are only for his Friends, and Relations, who come to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce with him, as is uſual upon ſuch ſolemn Occaſions.</q> Thus the Conſpirators might Apologiſe for themſelves, when they were intimately Conſcious that this Thankſ-giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (with all the <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Hoſpitality</hi> which did attend it) was deſign'd as a Prologue unto the moſt Diſmal Tragedy, <hi>the Murther of the beſt of Kings.</hi> The <hi>Devil</hi> has in all Ages brought about his moſt Pernicious Stratagems under the ſhew of Sanctity. He's willing that men ſhou'd profeſs as much Godlineſs as they pleaſe, if he may but have the Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it. He very well underſtands his own Intereſt, and is too cunning to forbid his Proſelytes the uſe of all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: Upon Condition that they will be Employ'd in the Way of Schiſm, and Sedition, he allows them to dreſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with all the External Ornaments of Holineſs. If he hath ſecur'd all within, and be certain that Hypocriſie lyes lurking in the Heart, when a ſplendid Zeal appears on the out-ſide, he's very well ſatisfy'd, and fears no Evil from the Long and Tedious Exerciſes of ſuch Religious Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banks.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64295:11"/>Let <hi>Abſalom</hi> himſelf, and his wicked Accomplices, pretend to be as Godly as they will at <hi>Hebron;</hi> and <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi>'s Zeal, he know's, ſo long as it is Confin'd unto <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> promotes his Kingdom. He is not diſpleas'd with the <hi>Phariſee</hi> for his long Prayers, and Frequent Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, if after theſe ſeeming Devotions, and Auſterities, he falls upon his Buſineſs, and Robs the Poor Widows houſe, which he pretends to have Sanctify'd by his Religious Per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>formances.</p>
            <p n="4">(IV.) By theſe and ſuch like Arts as I have mention'd, the <hi>Conſpiracy waxed Strong,</hi> and the <hi>People Encreaſed Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally with Abſalom.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">His Majeſties Declaration, &amp;c. p. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>And as their Numbers En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, ſo did their Boldneſs:</hi> Now they thought that all was ſure, and therefore<note n="*" place="margin">Ib. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Truſting no longer to the ſlow Methods of Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they betook themſelves to Arms.</hi> And if <hi>Ahitophel</hi>'s Counſel had been taken, He, with his 12000 Men, wou'd have <hi>Maſter'd</hi> thoſe Souldiers which attended the King; and not onely have Seiz'd, but have Kill'd the King Himſelf. Things being come to this height, there was no looking back, or thinking of a Reconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Thoſe who are engag'd in ways of Wickedneſs, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in this <hi>Bewitching ſin of Rebellion,</hi> endeavour to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure themſelves, by adding one ſin unto another, hopeing for no Protection for their ſmaller Crimes, but by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of greater. The firſt Beginnings of Treaſon are care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully nouriſh'd, 'till they break out into open defiance; and what at firſt, perhaps, deſerved only the more gentle name of Ingratitude, by degrees encreaſes into a moſt horrid Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy: When the <hi>Houſe is thus ſwept and garniſhed,</hi> and <hi>this one Devil</hi> hath taken poſſeſſion, <hi>ſeven Devils</hi> greater than the firſt, ſoon joyn themſelves to his Company. Rebels ſeldom have the Grace to Repent, but proceed from one Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity to another, till Treaſon grows big with Revenge, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64295:12"/>the Cloud, which at firſt could ſcarcely be diſcern'd, ſwells 'till it fall upon the Earth in the Showers, Whirle-winds, and Tempeſts of a Civil-War. When men have once caſt off that Allegiance, which they owe unto God, and the King, they hold it Ignoble to Retreat; but to perſevere in their Sin, they account a Sign of a generous Diſpoſition. Such an <hi>Anti-chriſtian Policy</hi> is that by which Rebellious Counſels are manag'd; and ſuch falſe Apprehenſions have they of Shame and Honour, who ſeem ſo much Concern'd, leſt they ſhould incur the one, or loſe the other. <hi>Ahitophel,</hi> who has ſo long been the Grand Contriver, ſcorns at laſt to become a puiſney Penitent, but proceeds to Execute that Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Miſchief, which before he had projected. <hi>I will ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>fall upon David, while he is Weary and Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>handed,</hi> Ch. XVII. 2. <hi>David</hi> and his Men (it might well be ſuppoſed) were tyred with their long and haſty March; and particularly He (being afflicted with the Thoughts of his Son's Vileneſs, and the Guilt which he thereby had Contracted) was, it might be preſumed, unfit for any Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as 'tis ſaid that the hands of <hi>Saul's Son became feeble, when he heard of Abner</hi>'s <hi>Death,</hi> Ch. IV. 1. So that in all Probability, this ſudden and unexpected Aſſault would have put a Period unto the King's Life, and Government. For what Reſiſtance could Languiſhing and Diſconſolate Weakneſs have made againſt Confident and well Appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Strength?</p>
            <p>And it may be further obſerv'd, That his Counſel was as Malicious, as it was Cunning, and favour'd as much of Tranſcendent Wickedneſs, as it did of Compleat Subtlety. What greater baſeneſs is there, than to take advantage of mens Misfortunes? and <hi>to Perſecute thoſe whom God hath Smitten?</hi> But we muſt not expect to find either honeſty or ingenuity in <hi>Ahitophel's</hi> Counſels, eſpecially when his caſe ſeems deſperate, and requires an immediate Execution. He
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64295:12"/>was Fearful leſt delays might have brought him into dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: He fear'd time wou'd have diſcover'd the Falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of <hi>Abſalom</hi>'s Cauſe, and have reduc'd the <hi>diſcontented Commons</hi> to their former Allegiance. Therefore (according to the Rules of his Policy) he will not let ſlip this Critical Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity. Upon Mature Deliberation the People might have ſeen, and been Convinc'd of their Errour; And he who Plotted againſt the life of <hi>Good King David,</hi> by a <hi>legal Tryal,</hi> might have loſt his own. He Foreſaw that the <hi>Verdict</hi> of an <hi>Honeſt Jury,</hi> wou'd have pronounc'd him Guilty; ſo that he could not be ſafe, but by the preſent Deſtruction of the <hi>Lords Anointed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">(V.) <hi>But the Divine Providence, which had hitherto preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi> David <hi>through the whole courſe of his life, did at this time in an Extraordinary Manner, ſhew it ſelf in the wonderful and gracious Deliverance of</hi> him, and his deareſt Relations, <hi>and all his loving Subjects, from this horrid and damnable Conſpiracy. David</hi> all this while meditates no Revenge againſt his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. He uſes no other Weapons but his <hi>Prayers and Tears.</hi> He inceſſantly beſeeches God, that he would forgive his <hi>Perſecutors and Slanderers, and that he would turn their Hearts.</hi> And God, who accepts the Sacrifice of an Humble and a Contrite Heart, hear'd his Prayers, and had reſpect unto the Sorrows of his Broken Spirit, for preſently after he had put up his Earneſt Petition unto the Lord, that he would <hi>Turn the Counſel of Ahitophel into fooliſhneſs, Huſhai the</hi> Wiſe <hi>Archite meets him, with his Clothes rent, and Aſhes upon his head,</hi> as the Manner of Mourners was in thoſe days. Here God began to anſwer <hi>David</hi>'s Prayer, provideing a man whoſe Wiſdom qualify'd him to confound <hi>Ahitophel,</hi> and turn his Stratagems into his own ruin. <hi>Huſhai</hi> (prompted by his Loyalty and Dutiful Affections) would have Waited upon the King in his Afflictions: But <hi>David</hi> knew his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities, and thought he might do him more Service at this
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:64295:13"/>time in <hi>Abſalom</hi>'s Court, than his own. Wherefore he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders him to return to the City, and to behave himſelf ſo as to gain <hi>Abſalom</hi>'s Favour, that (having his Countenance) he might be able to defeat the Counſel of <hi>Ahitophel.</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly <hi>Huſhai</hi> ſalutes <hi>Abſalom</hi> as King, tenders his ſervice unto him, and is admtted into his Secrets.</p>
            <p>And now he, and <hi>Ahitophel,</hi> are the two Grand-Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, and the whole buſineſs is to be Tranſacted by their directions. After other lewd and damnable Advice, <hi>Ahitophel</hi> gives that moſt pernicious Counſel before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd; which was, that he with 12000 men ſhould pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue after <hi>David</hi> that very Night. But God, who Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rules the Hearts of all men, did move <hi>Abſalom</hi> not to reſolve, till he had alſo Conſulted <hi>Huſhai</hi> about this Weighty Affair, <hi>Call now for Huſhai</hi> (ſays he) <hi>and let us hear</hi> what he ſaith. And when he was come, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded the Queſtion to him, <hi>Shall we do after this Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner? If not, ſpeak thou,</hi> Ch. XVII. 5, 6. <hi>Abſalom</hi> ſeems to have been very well ſatisfy'd with what <hi>Ahitophel</hi> had propounded, and to have Conſulted <hi>Huſhai,</hi> rather as one whom he was unwilling to make his Enemy, than to truſt as a Friend, and therefore 'tis likely did put no great Confidence in him. <hi>Let us</hi> however <hi>hear</hi> ſaith he ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) <hi>likewiſe what he ſaith.</hi> But when <hi>Huſhai</hi> had deliver'd his Opinion, he was ſtrangely pleas'd with it, inſomuch that he reſolves to Act according to his Direction. <q>He repreſenteth the danger which might have ariſen from a ſudden Surpriſe. <hi>Davids</hi> men, he tells him, would fight it out to the laſt. That to be ſure <hi>David</hi> lay in Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſh, was hid in ſome Pit, or ſafe place, and would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly fall upon ſome part of the Army, and defea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them, put the other to flight. Then he ſuits his language to the proud humour of the Vain-glorious Prince. He counſels, <hi>that all Iſrael be gathered together, even
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:64295:13"/>from Dan unto Beerſheba, as the ſand that is by the Sea for Multitude.</hi> That he himſelf (like a couragious General) ſhould Command them in Perſon. Thus he tells him, that he might promiſe himſelf Succeſs. Such a numerous Army would fall upon him, <hi>as the dew upon the ground:</hi> And if he was fled to any City, wou'd be <hi>able to draw him and the City it ſelf, and all his Company, into the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abſalom's</hi> youthful Fancy was hugely ſtruck with theſe big Words, and hyperbolical Expreſſions; ſo <hi>Ahitophel</hi>'s Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice not taking Effect, <hi>David</hi> gains time to ſtrengthen, and prepare himſelf with neceſſary Proviſions againſt the danger with which he was encompaſſed. <hi>Huſhai</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently acquaints <hi>Zadok</hi> and <hi>Abiathar</hi> with what had paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; and leſt <hi>Abſalom</hi> (being fickle) ſhould alter his Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, he adviſes them to ſend word unto <hi>David,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Lodge not this night in the plains of the Wilderneſs, but ſpeedily paſs over Jordan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this management of <hi>Huſhai,</hi> we may obſerve a rare mixture of <hi>Obedience, Faithfulneſs,</hi> and <hi>Diſcretion.</hi> Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is uſually jealous of unexpected Friendſhip, and <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalom</hi> (taking his newly reconciled Enemy for a Spy) might probably have deliver'd him over unto preſent Execution. But his <hi>clear ſpirit</hi> was not moved with this Conſideration. He fears not <hi>Abſalom's</hi> Diſpleaſure, when he acts in obedience unto <hi>David</hi>'s Commands. Beſides, had he been an <hi>Ahitophel,</hi> and not an <hi>Huſhai,</hi> had he been a Wicked, and not an Honeſt Politician, <hi>Abſalom</hi>'s greatneſs might have tempted him to have quitted <hi>David</hi>'s broken For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, and have courted the Affections of his Riſing son. But he (like a Faithful Subject) hates to be Treacherous to his Maſter, and chuſes rather to mourn with <hi>David</hi> in his Afflictions, than triumph with his Rebelious Subjects. And as his Obedience and Fidelity were remarkable in this
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64295:14"/>
               <hi>critical juncture,</hi> ſo his Conduct was exactly diſcreet in this great and dangerous Concern. He did not (like an officious <hi>Politico</hi>) intrude himſelf into <hi>Abſalom</hi>'s Preſence, but wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a convenient Opportunity, and ſtay'd 'till he was ask'd. And when he offer'd his Counſel 'twas with all due ſubmiſſion unto <hi>Ahitophel</hi>'s greater Wiſdom, onely at this time he beg'd leave to diſſent from him. <hi>The Counſel which Ahitophel hath given at this time is not good;</hi> And after he perceiv'd that <hi>Abſalom</hi> was of this Opinion, how careful is he to loſe no time? with what haſte doth he fly to the Prieſts, that they might immediately diſpatch a Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger unto the King?</p>
            <p n="2">2. They (extremely glad to hear ſo good News) forthwith obſerve his Inſtructions, which were, no doubt, that they ſhould acquaint the King with the whole ſtate of <hi>Abſalom's</hi> Affairs, as well as to deſire him to provide for his own preſent Safety. This they did by a ſilly Maid, whoſe tender Age, and Sex made her unfit for ſuch a piece of Service, had ſhe not been an Inſtrument in the hands of God, who by the moſt <hi>Contemptible Means</hi> doth often confound the <hi>Wiſdom of the Wiſe. By ſtrength alone no man can prevail. The Race is not always to the ſwift, nor the Battel to the ſtrong.</hi> King <hi>David</hi> at this time was not ſaved <hi>by the multitude of an Hoaſt,</hi> but by the deſpicable, and unarmed weakneſs of a ſingle Woman. <hi>Abiathar</hi> was at this time the High-prieſt, and <hi>Zadok</hi> next in order to him, but both of them <hi>David's</hi> faithful Servants; they had not learnt the New Doctrine of Reſiſtance, nor did they act by the Politick Rule of our Modern <hi>Laodiceans,</hi> who really neither eſpouſe the King's Cauſe, nor the Faction of his Enemies, but ſtand aloof off, till they may, with diſcretion, join themſelves to the ſtronger ſide. <hi>Zadok</hi> and <hi>Abiathar</hi> were as wiſe as they, but more honeſt; and tho' they were God's Prieſts, yet continued the Kings
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:64295:14"/>Loyal Subjects in his greateſt Diſtreſs and utmoſt Extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities. They were obedient unto <hi>David's</hi> Command; and continued in the City (tho' with no ſmall hazard of their lives) tho' it was known that they were no Friends unto <hi>Abſalom's</hi> Deſigns. I wiſh that ſome who term them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>the Miniſters of the Goſpel,</hi> would acquit themſelves in this reſpect, as well as theſe (howſoever deſpiſed) <hi>Prieſts of the Law.</hi> And it's well if the immoveable Loyalty of our Clergy to the Crown, be not the Chief Reaſon why they are treated, by her Enemies on both ſides, with ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and ſcorn. But if this be our only Crime, we own and glory in it: and are no more aſham'd to imitate the <hi>Jewiſh Prieſts</hi> in their Chriſtian Vertues, than we are to be called by their Name. We are ready to attend our Lord the King whitherſoever he goes; but if he ſhall pleaſe to order us <hi>to waite upon the Ark of God in Jeruſalem,</hi> we obey; and ſhall there (With <hi>Zadok</hi> and <hi>Abiathar</hi>) ſerve him to the utmoſt of our power, as well with our Daily Actions as Conſtant Prayers. But it may be thought that I do too much divert from my Subject, I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore return. And having obſerv'd <hi>Huſhai</hi>'s prudent Addreſs, <hi>Zadok</hi> and <hi>Abiathar's</hi> watchful Care for their Prince's Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; in the next place, this Great Deliverance muſt chiefly be aſcrib'd unto the good Providence of God, in whoſe <hi>hands are the hearts of Kings.</hi> Without the Divine Protection all Humane Means are weak and inſufficient. It was God alone <hi>who turned the counſel of Ahitophel into fooliſhneſs.</hi> He brought <hi>Huſhai</hi> to <hi>David</hi> in this exigence, mov'd him to ſend him back into the City, and enclin'd <hi>Abſalom</hi> to follow his counſel, tho' much worſe for his purpoſe than <hi>Ahitophel's.</hi> It was he who caus'd <hi>Zadok</hi> and <hi>Abiathar</hi> to remain in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and made them the happy Inſtruments of the King's Deliverance. Without his Providential Care, theſe <hi>Watchmen had waked but in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64295:15"/>vain.</hi> Theſe things did not happen by Fate or Chance, but by his Appointment who <hi>giveth Salvation unto Kings, and ſheweth Mercy unto his Anointed.</hi> Whatever men may propoſe unto themſelves, it is only in the <hi>Power</hi> of the <hi>Almighty</hi> to diſpoſe. The Politicians may Conſult, and the Souldiers fit their Arms; but (without God's per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion) neither the Counſels of the one, nor the Weapons of the other can prevail againſt King <hi>David.</hi> The Phariſees conſulted how to put <hi>Jeſus</hi> to death. And ſome profligate Villains had ſworn to take away S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s life, but neither can execute their malicious Purpoſes, when God ſhall pleaſe to interpoſe in the behalf of <hi>injur'd innocence: Abſalom</hi> with his Great Men may Rebel, and take <hi>Counſel againſt the Lord and againſt his Anointed;</hi> but <hi>he who dwelleth in Heaven ſhall laugh; the Lord ſhall have them in deriſion. He ſhall ſpeak unto them in his wrath, and vex them in his ſore diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</hi> Pſal. II. 2, 4, 5. He hearkens unto <hi>Davi'd</hi>'s Prayer; And by <hi>Huſhai's</hi> honeſt Policy, <hi>Zadok</hi> and <hi>Abiathar</hi>'s Loyal Piety, together with the diligent induſtry of a ſilly Maid, turns <hi>Abſalom's</hi> Strength into Weakneſs, and <hi>Ahitophel</hi>'s Wiſdom into Folly.</p>
            <p>And now having thus far purſued the Hiſtory of <hi>Abſalom</hi> and <hi>Ahitophel,</hi> I need not draw the Parallel betwixt this unnatural Rebellion and <hi>the Treaſonable Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy againſt his Majeſties Sacred Perſon, and Government, lately diſcoverd.</hi> 'Tis very evident that they do much reſemble one another, not only in the <hi>Principal Conſpirators,</hi> but alſo the <hi>Perſon</hi> againſt whom they were deſign'd, the <hi>Pretences</hi> by which they were carried on, the <hi>Progreſs</hi> which was made in them, and the <hi>happy Inſtruments,</hi> by which (next under God) they were diſcover'd. I had rather that thoſe who are Guilty ſhould make Application unto themſelves, Repent of their Wickedneſs, and for the future ſtrive (with the men of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi>) who ſhall expreſs the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:64295:15"/>greateſt Duty, and Loyalty to the Lord their King; than (by calling to their remembrance the miſerable Ends of <hi>Abſalom</hi> and <hi>Ahitophel</hi>) to put them in mind of that Divine Vengeance which attends <hi>obdurate Rebels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If guilty Engliſhmen ſhall with <hi>Shimei,</hi> become ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of their ſin, and make an unſeigned ſubmiſſion, I do not envy their admittance unto the King's Grace and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour; But if they (neither fearing God, nor the King) ſhall ſtill perſiſt in the ways of <hi>Schiſm and Sedition;</hi> If they (like <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi>) ſhall ſtill continue <hi>Brethren in Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity;</hi> have not <hi>the Innocent</hi> and <hi>the Loyal</hi> reaſon to pray with good old <hi>Jacob,</hi> that <hi>their ſouls may not come into their Secrets,</hi> nor their <hi>honour be united unto their Aſſemblies?</hi> That (when dead) the memory of their <hi>fierce Anger,</hi> and <hi>cruel Wrath</hi> may be accurſed: And (whilſt alive) that they may be <hi>divided in Jacob, and ſcattered in Iſrael?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Give me leave further to obſerve, That as this Engliſh Conſpiracy doth in moſt things anſwer that of <hi>Abſalom</hi>'s (inſomuch that it may ſeem to have been tranſcrib'd from this Original, by thoſe who abuſe the <hi>Scriptures unto their own damnation</hi>) ſo they do both agree in ſetting aſide the Title of <hi>Heriditary Succeſſion.</hi> For <hi>Abſalom</hi> (as hath been obſerv'd) had an Elder Brother, who was the undoubted Heir, as long as <hi>King David</hi> had not nomintaed, nor <hi>God Almighty</hi> appointed another <hi>Succeſſour. Abſalom</hi> indeed was begotten in lawful Wedlock, and the Kingdom of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was not then firmly ſettled, upon the Right of Hereditary Succeſſion, as our <hi>Engliſh Monarchy</hi> is, and has been in all Ages. In theſe reſpects <hi>Abſalom</hi> had a better Plea than any Pretender to the Engliſh Crown can produce. No wonder therefore, that thoſe who plotted againſt his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majeſty, ſhould alſo deſign to imbrue their wicked hands in the Blood of his <hi>Royal Highneſs, his deareſt Brother, and only Lawful Succeſſour.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:64295:16"/>
            <p> Had God permitted this horrid Conſpiracy to have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Effect, I cannot ſufficiently expreſs, nor you fully conceive the Conſequence which wou'd have followed this <hi>Bloody Tragedy.</hi> Their <hi>Golden Pretences</hi> would have ſoon vaniſh'd into nothing, and Diſmal Confuſion would have cover'd the face of the whole Nation. Our Churches would have been defil'd with the raveing madneſs of <hi>Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks.</hi> Inſtead of enjoying our juſt <hi>Liberties,</hi> Slavery and Impriſonment would have been our doom: and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty</hi> would have been ſwallowed up in the unſatiable Abyſs of Sacriledge and Covetouſneſs. <hi>Violence and Strife</hi> would have domineer'd in the <hi>City; Miſchief and Injury</hi> would have reign'd in the <hi>Country; Deceit and Guile</hi> would have walk'd publickly in all our Streets. In ſhort, the State would have been deſtroyed by War and Oppreſſion. The <hi>Church</hi> would have been buried under the Rubbiſh of Heretical Opinions, and endleſs Diviſions. But I ſhall not endeavour to number the Miſeries which would have enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, had God ſuffered this Execrable Villany to have been acted. I ſhall rather excite you to joyn with me in a thankful Commemoration of God's unſpeakable Mercy, in protecting, from the Fury of their Cruel Enemies, <hi>Our moſt Gracious, Juſt, and Wiſe King, his deareſt Brother; and with them the whole Royal Family, all his Loyal Subjects, this A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolick Church, and ſinful Nation.</hi> Every <hi>good Chriſtian,</hi> and <hi>Loyal Subject</hi> cannot but rejoice in ſecret for this ſignal Deliverance. Much more will he chearfully, and devoutly return his ſolemn Thanks in Publick for the ſame, and ſay,</p>
            <p>Bleſſed be God who hath <hi>heard the King in the day of his Trouble, and defended</hi> him <hi>from the Inſurrections of Wicked-doers:</hi> Who hath ſent <hi>him Help out of his Sanctuary, and ſtrengthned him out of Sion;</hi> Who by his Miraculous Providence, did reinſtate him in the Throne of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: who hath all his life long protected him from dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:64295:16"/>and hath ſo lately in a wonderful manner <hi>deliver'd his ſoul from the Battel which was againſt him:</hi> Who hath prevented the Deſigns of <hi>Blood-thirſty and Deceitful men,</hi> and hath brought them <hi>into that Pit of Deſtruction,</hi> which they had digged for <hi>his Anointed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bleſſed be God, who, together with him, hath <hi>preſerv'd his deareſt Brother:</hi> that they, who were to have been Companions in death, do ſtill live and rejoice together in <hi>ſinging Praiſes unto the God of their Salvation.</hi> Bleſſed be God who hath <hi>lifted up the light of his countenance upon the whole Royal Family, and hath broken the ſnares in pieces which</hi> were laid for them; Who hath <hi>ſmitten their Enemies upon the cheek-bone,</hi> and ſecur'd them <hi>from</hi> 10000<hi>'s of the People, who had ſet themſelves againſt them round about.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bleſſed be God, who hath looked upon the <hi>hearty deſires of his humble ſervants, the King's Loyal Subjects:</hi> Who hath <hi>kept</hi> them <hi>from ſhame and rebuke,</hi> and ſaved them from their Enemies, who would have <hi>ſwallowed them up quick, when they were ſo wrathfully diſpleaſed at them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bleſſed be God, who by defeating the Counſels of the Wicked, hath prevented thoſe Puniſhments which the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of this Nation, for their ſins, had juſtly deſerv'd: Who has not cut-off a ſinful and ungrateful People in their Iniquities; but hath given them time to repent, and turn unto their <hi>God, and their Soveraign Lord the King,</hi> againſt whom they have moſt grievouſly offended.</p>
            <p>Bleſſed and for ever bleſſed be our God, who hath <hi>beheld and viſited that Vine which his own right hand hath plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in theſe Kingdoms:</hi> Who hath not ſuffer'd <hi>her hedge to be broke down, nor they which go by to pluck off her grapes.</hi> Who hath not permitted <hi>the Wilde Boar of the wood to root it up,</hi> nor <hi>the wilde Beaſt of the field to devour it:</hi> Who haſt remembred <hi>this Congregation which</hi> he hath <hi>purchaſed of old, the Kingdom</hi> of his <hi>Inheritance,</hi> which he
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:64295:17"/>hath <hi>redeem'd;</hi> This <hi>Mount Sion wherein</hi> he has <hi>dwelt:</hi> Who has not <hi>delivered the ſoul</hi> of his <hi>Turtle-dove unto the Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of the Wicked: Who hath reſtrain'd his Enemies from caſting Fire into his Sanctuary, and deſtroying the Dwelling-place of his Holy Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. To Conclude, Who hath defended our Church from thoſe who had ſaid in their hearts, Let us deſtroy her; who does yet continue unto her, and all her faithful Children, <hi>Apoſtolick Doctrine, Government, and Diſcipline;</hi> together with her <hi>convenient Poſſeſſions;</hi> ſo that <hi>Hereſie, Schiſm, Profaneneſs and Sacriledge</hi> have not hitherto triumphed in her Ruine. For theſe and all other Mercies, contained and implyed in this Great Deliverance which we now Comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morate, <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord God of Iſrael from everlaſting, to everlaſting, And let all the People ſay,</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
